hi guys today we're going to look at how
we can use the unity terrain tool to
easily create landscapes in our game
we'll look at how to sculpt the terrain
how to add textures
and how we can add scenery such as trees
and flowers
okay we're going to start with this
scene that has a character that can run
around
we created this scene in the earlier
videos of our 3d platformer series
so take a look if you want to know how
it was done
we're going to delete the basic scenery
we have at the moment and create
something a bit more interesting for our
character to explore
by default our project has the basic
terrain tools installed
unity also provides additional terrain
tools via an optional package
to install this we'll go to window
package manager
at the moment these tools are in preview
so we need to enable preview packages
to do this we'll click on the cog icon
and select advanced project settings
we'll then check the enable preview
packages check box
back in the package manager we'll search
for terrain tools
and we'll install this package
in the package description there's a
button to install sample assets
clicking this will take us to the asset
store where we can install some
additional terrain brushes and textures
we'll click open in unity and import
them into our project
now we've got everything we need to get
started
we'll open the terrain toolbox by
clicking on window terrain terrain
toolbox
from here we can change various settings
such as the width and length of the
terrain
we'll leave everything as it is and
click the create button
this has now created a blank flat
terrain
next we'll reposition our character to
place it on the terrain
we'll select it in the hierarchy and
change the position to 250 on the x-axis
and 5 on the z-axis let's press play to
make sure everything is working as
expected
our character can run along the terrain
but it's not very exciting at the moment
let's stop the game and look at how we
can add some mountains and hills
we'll select the terrain in the
hierarchy and click the paint terrain
icon in the inspector
from this drop down we have several
tools we can choose from
we'll start by looking at the raise and
lower terrain tool
we can choose from one of the many brush
types and simply click on the terrain to
raise
it if we want to lower the terrain we
can hold down the control key and click
again
in the inspector we can change various
settings on the brush
the brush strength determines how much
the terrain is raised or lowered
we can use the shortcut key a and move
the mouse to quickly change the strength
in the scene view
we can also change the size of the brush
we can use the shortcut key s
to change this in the scene view we can
also rotate the brush
pressing the shortcut key d allows us to
do this easily in the scene view
we're going to select one of the
mounting brushes and use it to paint a
mountain range around the boundary of
our terrain
we'll also add a mountain in the center
the next thing we're going to do is
flatten out the area we want our
character to be able to move on
to do this we'll select the set height
tool
this allows us to set a height that we
want to set the terrain to
we'll set the desired height to 0.2
we'll select one of the round brushes
and then paint around the edges of our
mountains
this will create steep edges that will
prevent our character from being able to
walk up the mountains
the problem we have now is that the
ground looks a bit too flat and
unnatural
we can improve this using the noise tool
this tool just paints random noise onto
our terrain
we can modify the noise to create
different effects
if we zoom out on the noise preview it
will create lots of small detail on our
terrain
and if we zoom in it will create larger
more subtle changes
we'll leave it zoomed in and set the
strength of the brush to 0.5
we'll then just paint over our flat area
with this brush to add a bit of
variation
this has probably added in a bit too
much variation to our terrain in places
we can fix this using the smooth height
tool
we'll just paint over the terrain to
smooth it out a little
now that we've sculpted our terrain
we'll change the rotation of our camera
so that we get a better view into the
distance
we'll select our virtual camera in the
hierarchy and change the rotation on the
x-axis to 15.
we also need to raise our character
slightly to position it on top of the
terrain
now let's press play to see it in action
things are starting to look a bit more
interesting now the next stage is to add
some textures
let's stop the game and select the
terrain in the hierarchy
we'll then select paint texture from the
drop down
before we can paint anything we need to
add some texture layers
we can either create a new layer and
select the texture we want
or we can add an existing one the asset
we installed earlier contains some
pre-defined texture layers so we'll use
one of those
we'll click add layer then we'll select
the rock texture layer
our terrain is now completely covered in
a rock texture
it doesn't look quite right at the
moment though let's open the layer
properties and have a look
the first thing we're going to change is
the normal scale this is a multiplier
for the normal map and essentially
determines how bumpy our rock looks
if we set this to zero our rock texture
looks flat and if we set it to 1 it
looks much better
the other setting will change is the
tiling size this determines how often
the texture repeats across the terrain
we'll set this to 20 on the x and y axis
press play to see how this looks
our mountains are now looking more
realistic but it's a very rocky world at
the moment
let's stop the game and add some grass
for some reason there isn't a grass
layer included in the sample asset pack
so we'll go back to the asset store and
search for fantasy landscape
we'll add this asset
then we'll open it in unity and import
it into our project
this asset contains a grass texture
layer and also contains trees and other
details that we'll use later
now we can go back to our terrain layers
and add in the grass layer
then we can just paint where we want the
grass to go
if we press play now we can see things
are looking much better
the next thing we'll do is add some
paths we'll stop the game and add the
road layer
we'll set the brush size to 15 and then
paint some parts on the grass
let's press play to see how this looks
we have some paths for our character but
they look very painted on at the moment
we can make this look much better by
making grass banks alongside the path
let's stop the game and select the raise
or lower terrain tool
now we'll hold down control and paint
along our path to lower the terrain
we'll then raise and lower the terrain
around the path to sculpt the banks
then we'll select the smooth height tool
and use it to smooth out the banks
we'll increase the blur radius to smooth
it out further
we'll need to reposition our character
again so that it stands on the path
let's press play to try this out
now the path is looking much better the
next thing we're going to look at is how
to add trees
let's stop the game and select the
terrain in the hierarchy
we'll then select the paint trees button
we'll click the edit trees button and
click
add tree we'll select the birch tree 1
prefab
and click add
now we can paint the tree onto our
terrain
and if we want to remove any trees we
can hold down the control key
there's also a button to mass place
trees
this lets you enter the number of trees
you want and it will then distribute
them across the entire terrain
as we don't want trees on our mountains
this doesn't really work but it can be
useful on flatter terrain
we'll lower the tree density and just
scatter some trees around on the grass
areas
to add some variety we'll add a couple
of other tree prefabs
we'll add the oak tree
and we'll add the deciduous tree
we'll then just paint some of these
around as well
let's press play to see how things are
looking now
it looks much better with the trees but
we now have this weird effect where the
trees seem to come to life as we
approach them
what is actually happening is that the
tree mesh is being replaced by a
billboard of the tree when it is in the
distance
a billboard is a flat 2d image that is
always facing the camera
then as we get closer it's transitioning
to the real mesh
the reason this is done is so that the
performance of the game isn't impacted
by drawing high detailed trees in the
distance
it's far too noticeable at the moment
though so we'll stop the game and go
into the terrain settings
we'll set the billboard start to 300.
this should make the transition from
billboard to mesh happen far enough away
that we don't really notice
another thing that we can do is add a
bit of fog to our scene
this will improve the overall appearance
of the scene and hide some of the
distant billboard trees
to do this we'll go to window rendering
lighting
we'll click on the environment tab and
enable the fog checkbox
we'll set the density of the fog to
0.002
okay let's press play to try it out
now as we move through the scene there's
no noticeable movement in the trees
there is a bit of a problem with the
lighting on our trees though
at the moment they are not being
affected by the environment lighting
which is causing them to look too dark
if we stop the game and go to the readme
that came with the asset
we can see the reason why
it says the skybox environment lighting
in the scene does not affect the tree's
shader
if you want to make the trees brighter
or darker select gradient or color
instead
let's go back to our lighting settings
to do this
we'll select the environment tab and
then change the environment lighting
source to color
we can then select the ambient color and
increase the intensity to brighten up
our trees
now everything is looking much brighter
the next thing we're going to do is add
some detail like grass and flowers
to do this we'll select the terrain in
the hierarchy and select the paint
details button
we'll then select the edit details
button from here we have a couple of
options
we can either add a texture or a mesh a
texture would work a bit like our
billboard trees
we could paint 2d images of grass or
flowers around and they would always
face the camera
this would look ok but the asset we
imported comes with a few detailed
meshes which would look much better
we'll select add detail mesh and select
the grass prefab
in here we can set the width and height
settings for the grass as well as the
colour tint we want to apply to healthy
and dry grass
we'll leave everything as it is for now
and click add
we can then paint the grass detail onto
our terrain
again we can hold down control to delete
the detail
we'll reduce the opacity of our brush to
reduce the density of the grass
then we'll paint patches of grass detail
all over our grass texture
let's press play to try this out
our grass isn't looking too great it's
swaying far too much and the colour and
size doesn't look right
let's stop the game and see how we can
fix this
we'll click on the edit details button
and then on edit in the drop-down
we'll change the minimum width to 0.7
and we'll set the maximum width to 1.2
we'll then set the height values to
match
we'll change the healthy color to a
light gray to take away most of the tint
we'll change the dry color to a dark
green color
that's improved the size and color the
next thing we need to do is stop the
grass swaying so much
we'll click on the terrain settings and
then go to the wind settings for the
grass
we'll set the bending value to 0.15
this will reduce the amount the grass
bends in the wind let's press play again
the grass is now looking much better
if we look into the distance we can see
the grass appearing as we walk towards
it
this is because grass in the distance is
cold to improve performance
we can make this look less noticeable by
stopping the game and increasing the
detail distance to 250
if we press play again the grass is now
visible in the distance
next we'll add in some more details
we'll stop the game and add in another
detail mesh
this time we'll select the mushroom
prefab
we'll set the minimum width to 1.1 and
the maximum width to 1.5
we'll then set the height values to
match
we'll set both the tint colors to a gray
color
as we don't want our mushrooms to sway
in the wind we also need to change the
render mode from grass to vertex lit
we'll click add and then select the
mushrooms
we'll lower the opacity of the brush and
then paint a few around the scene
we'll then add another detail mesh and
select the flower 2 prefab
set the minimum width to 1 and the
maximum width to 1.5
we'll then set the height values to
match
we'll set the healthy color to a gray
color
we'll set the dry color to have a very
slight red tint
we'll click add and then paint them onto
the terrain
we'll press play to see how this looks
now we have trees grass flowers and
mushrooms and this variety makes the
scene look much more natural
we'll stop the game and add in one final
detail
the asset we imported also comes with a
rock prefab
we'll drag a few of these into the scene
to add some extra detail
we'll rotate them to give them some
variation
we'll then lower them slightly so they
look like they're embedded in our
terrain
let's press play to have a look at our
final result
we've now built a vibrant landscape for
our player to explore
in future videos we'll look at how we
can improve this further by adding
gameplay elements such as collectibles
and enemies
okay that covers everything for this
video hope you found it useful please
leave any questions or feedback in the
comments and subscribe and click the
bell icon so you don't miss the next one
if you find the channel useful and would
like to help support our work you can
find us on patreon and coffee.com
thanks guys